In this video we're going to move on to the next major feature inside of MCP servers which is
resources. To help you understand resources we're going to be implementing another feature inside
of our project. Here's what we're going to add in. I want to allow a user to mention a document by
putting in an at symbol and then the name of a document. Whenever they do so I want to automatically
fetch the contents of that document and insert it into the prompt that we send off to Claude.
So in total there's going to be kind of two aspects to this feature. Whenever a user types
out the at symbol inside of a message we're going to automatically show a list of all the different
documents that they can mention inside of a little autocomplete window. Then whenever a user submits
a message with a mention inside of it we're going to automatically get the contents of that document
and insert it into the prompt that we send off to Claude. So for example if a user says something
like what's in the at report.pdf file I would want to assemble a prompt like this and send it to
Claude. So we're going to have the query inside there from the user and then we're also going to
tell Claude that the user might have referenced some document and here is the contents of the
document. So the approach here or the idea here is that we will not have to rely upon Claude to go
and make use of some tool to figure out what is inside of the report.pdf file. Instead the user
can just preemptively mention the file and we're going to automatically insert some context ahead
of time. Now one thing I want to clarify here is that we're kind of talking about two separate
features. The first feature is that whenever a user types in the at symbol we really need the
MCP server to give us a list of all the different documents that the user can possibly mention.
And then the second aspect here is that whenever a user submits a message that contains a mention
then we need the MCP server to give us the contents of a single document. To get this
information out of our MCP server we are going to be making use of resources. Resources allow our
MCP server to expose some amount of data to the client. We usually define one resource for each
distinct read operation. So in our example we need to get a list of documents and read the contents
of a single document. So we would probably end up making two separate resources. One resource would
be responsible for returning just a list of document names so we can put them inside the
autocomplete and then we would probably make another resource that will expose the contents
of a single document based upon its document id. When we define these resources they are going to
be accessed through our MCP client. So the entire flow that we're going to eventually put together
here whenever a user types in something like what's in the at and then presumably they're going
to put in something right there. As soon as they type in that at character we need to display a
list of document names to put in the autocomplete. So our code is going to reach out to the MCP
client which in turn is going to send a read resource request off to the MCP server. Inside
of that read resource request we're going to include something called the URI. That is essentially the
address of the resource we want to read. This URI gets defined whenever we put together our resource
initially. So the URI is that right there. When we send off this read resource request the MCP server
is going to look at the exact URI that we put inside of here and then run the function we put
together right there. Take the result and send it back to us inside of a read resource result message.
We can then take the data inside there and display it inside of our autocomplete or do whatever else
we need to do with it. There are two different types of resources direct and templated. You'll
also sometimes see direct resources referred to as static resources. A direct resource just has a
static URI so it's always going to be the exact same thing such as docs colon slash slash documents.
A templated resource will have one or more parameters inside of its URI. So for example
we might have document slash and then kind of a wild card right here so we can put in any document
id we want to. And whenever we ask for this resource that document id right there inside
the URI will be automatically parsed by the Python MCP SDK and provided as a keyword argument to our
function. The keyword argument will have the exact same name of whatever string you put in right there.
So doc id right there will be doc id right there. As you can probably guess we'll make use of
templated resources anytime that we want to allow a little bit more selection or variety or
customization in what someone is asking for out of our MCP server. Implementing resources is pretty
straightforward so let's go back over to our editor and we're going to add in some resources to our
server right away. All right so back over inside my editor I will find the mcpserver.py file.
I'm then going to scroll down a little bit and I'm going to find some comments for writing resource
to return all document ids and writing resource to return the contents of a particular document.
Now for this first one right here I put in the comment document ids. Remember for us our document
ids are essentially the name of the document so for us we're really just returning these ids they're
going to serve the purpose of the name that means we can put them directly into that autocomplete
element. All right so to make our resource I'm going to delete that to do and then I'll add in
a mcp.resource. The first argument is going to be the URI for accessing this thing. Again it's kind
of equivalent to a route handler so I will use docs colon slash slash documents and I'm also
going to add in a mime type of application slash json. A resource can return any type of data so it
can be plain text, it can be json, it can be binary data, anything. It's up to us to kind of give our
client a hint as to what kind of data we are returning. To do so we're going to define this
mime type. A mime type of application slash json is a hint to our client who's eventually going to
ask for this resource right here that we're going to be sending back a string that contains some
structured json data and so it would be up to our client to deserialize that data or essentially
turn it into some usable data structure. Underneath that decorator I'll write out my function of list
docs and I'm going to return a list of strings and then inside there I will return list docs
keys. So just take all the keys out of that dictionary and turn it into a list and I'm going
to return it. Now you'll notice that we are not returning distinct json here in other words we're
not actually returning a string. The mcp python sdk is going to automatically take whatever we
return and turn it into a string for us. All right let's take care of our second resource. So I'm
going to delete that comment and then replace it with mcp resource docs colon slash slash documents
and then this time I want a templated resource because I'm putting in this wildcard right here
and then my mime type this time around just for a little bit of variety I'm going to be returning
plain text because it's going to be just the contents of the document and I'm not going to
wrap it up in any kind of structure. Now just so you know in a real application something like
read a document I would probably return an entire document record so some kind of dictionary that
contains maybe the id the content the author name the author id and stuff like that but just for the
sake of an example I'm going to return just the text of the document to show you how we would
normally return plain text. So in this scenario my mime type would be text plain and then I will
make fetch doc I'm going to take doc id which is going to be a string and I'm going to return a
string. Once again whatever word you put right there it's going to show up as a keyword argument
inside of your function. If we added in some additional parameters inside of here such as
maybe doc type or something like that it would just show up as an additional keyword argument
like so. Then inside of here I'm going to first make sure that the id that this person is asking
for actually exists so if doc id not in docs I'm going to raise a value error with a f string that
says doc with id not found and then if we get past that check I'll return docs doc id and that's
it. Now let's try testing this stuff out inside of our mcp inspector once again so remember at
our terminal we can run the command uv run mcp dev mcp server.py that's going to start up a web
server at port 6277 or excuse me 6274 is the default so I can make sure I open that up inside
my browser. Here we go I'll click connect I'll then find resources and then I should be able to
list out all the different resources that are available. Now when I list out resources this
is going to be specifically static or direct resources so I'll see only docs slash documents
and then I can separately list out all my different resource templates and so I'll see
that I have one resource template of fetch doc. I'm going to first try to run the slash documents
right here we'll see what we get back so this is the actual message the exact structure that gets
returned from our mcp server. You'll notice that it has a text property and inside there is all the
data that we are returning serialized as a json string so again it would be up to us inside of
our cli application to take this text right here and deserialize it from this json string into a
usable list of strings. Then we can also test out fetch doc so I'll click on that I have to enter a
doc id so I'm going to put it in I want to read the report.pdf file and I'll read the resource
and now I should see the contents of that particular document and you'll notice this
time around once again I get a text plain so that's a hint to me that this is plain text
and I should not attempt to deserialize it from json in any way.